RG069:151, Joseph S. Longo Papers
Connecticut State Library
Joseph S. Longo papers
1932-1996
Connecticut State Library
Longo, Joseph S.
3 cubic feet
Joseph S. Longo (1914-1993) served as a Justice of the Connecticut Supreme Court from 1975 to 1979.
RG069_151
2010-014
Biographical Note
Judge Longo was born in Norwich on September 22, 1914. He graduated from Norwich Free Academy and Yale University, where he received his B.A. degree in 1936. He enrolled at the Boston University School of Law, where he received his law degree in 1939. He was admitted to the Connecticut bar that same year.
Judge Longo entered the practice of law in Norwich in partnership with Attorney James J. Dutton, Jr., and later served in the United States Navy during World War II. His political career included terms in the state House of Representatives from 1949 to 1951 and in the state Senate from 1951 to 1955. He was majority leader and chair of the Judiciary Committee during the 1955 session.
Judge Longo became a judge of the Norwich City Court in 1949. In 1957, he was nominated and confirmed to be a judge of the Court of Common Pleas. He was elevated to the Superior Court in 1959 and served on that court until 1975. During his tenure on the Superior Court, he served as chief judge from 1973 to 1975. Judge Longo became an associate justice of the Supreme Court in 1975 and served in that capacity until becoming a senior associate justice in 1979. He became a state trial referee in 1984 and continued to hear cases until the early 1990s.
Judge Longo died November 29, 1993, at the age of seventy-nine. At the time of his death, Chief Justice Ellen A. Peters noted: "Justice Longo's appointment to the Supreme Court was the culmination of a long and distinguished judicial career. As a judge of the Norwich City Court, the Court of Common Pleas and the Superior Court, Justice Longo epitomized the fair and hardworking jurist. On the Supreme Court, he continued to demonstrate his love for the law and for the betterment of society through the rule of law. To his colleagues as well as to those who argued before him, he was a much admired member of this court."
Source: "Memorials of Connecticut Judges and Attorneys As Printed in the Connecticut Reports, volume 228, page(s) 933-934, THE HONORABLE JOSEPH LONGO, 1914-1993", http://www.cslib.org/memorials/longoj.htm (viewed February 8, 2010.
Scope and Content
Series 1. Personal and Professional Papers, 1932-1996, contains biographical information, ephemera, judicial nomination and resignation papers, a list of cases authored while a Justice of the State Supreme Court, and news clippings. Series 2. Photographs, circa 1937-1989, includes family, as Justice of the Supreme Court, and General Assembly from Longo’s terms in the House and Senate. There are two souvenir albums of State Senators’ party for the Lieutenant-Governor. Series 3. Certificates, Awards, and Diplomas, 1932-1989, include academic diplomas, admission to the bar, certificates of election, judicial appointments, certificates of fraternal organization membership, and certificates of recognition.
Arrangement
Series 1. Personal and Professional Papers, 1932-1996, undated
Series 2. Photographs, circa 1937-1989
Series 3. Certificates, Awards, and Diplomas, 1932-1989
Related Material
None.
Index Terms
Persons:
Longo, Joseph S
Subjects:
Judges -- Connecticut
Places:
Norwich (Conn.)
Document Types:
Certificates; Clippings; Correspondence; Diplomas; Photographs
Restrictions on Access
See the policy.
Provenance
Donated by Joseph S. Longo's children on July 10, 2009.
Container List
- Series 1. Personal and Professional Papers, 1932-1996, undated
  - Academic papers, 1932-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes acceptance letters to Amherst College and Yale University, Boston University student id, and State bar examination paper with identification number.
  - Biographical information, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ephemera, 1951-1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes primarily testimonial dinner programs and invitations.
  - Judicial nomination and resignation papers, 1961-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - List of cases authored while a Justice of the Supreme Court, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Speech, "Remarks to New Citizens", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - News clippings, 1951-1996, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
- Series 2. Photographs, circa 1937-1989
  - Family, 1937-1940, undated; 5 photographs (Box 3)
    Photographs of Longo with his wife and daughters. Includes 2 wedding photographs.
  - Justice of the Supreme Court, 1975-1979; 8 photographs (Box 3)
  - Democratic Senators, 1955; 1 photograph (Box 3)
  - Souvenir album, Connecticut State Senator's party for the Lieutenant-Governor Edward N. Allen aboard a New Haven Railroad special train, 1953 May 14; 36 b&w photographs (Box 3)
    The photographs were removed from the binder. The binder is in Box 1.
  - Souvenir album, Connecticut State Senator's party for the Lieutenant-Governor Charles W. Jewett aboard a New Haven Railroad special train leaving Hartford, Conn., 1955 May 12; 39 b&w photographs (Box 3)
    A duplicate photograph not originally in the binder is stored with these photographs.
  - Unarranged, circa 1953-1989; 56 photographs (Box 3)
  - Panoramic photographs, 1947-1957 (Box 2)
    - All New England Elk's group, Huntington Library, Pasedena, Calif., 1947 July 10 (Box 2)
    - 50th anniversary of Norwich Lodge, No. 430, B.P.O. Elks at State Armory, Norwich, Conn., 1948 April 10 (Box 2)
    - Connecticut House of Representatives, Hon. John R. Thim, Speaker, Connecticut, 1949 April (Box 2)
    - Unidentified Elks banquet, circa 1950 (Box 2)
    - Senate, State of Connecticut, Lt. Governor Edward Allen, President, Hartford, Conn., 1951 March (Box 2)
    - Connecticut State Senate, State Capitol, Hartford, Connecticut, 1955 March (Box 2)
    - Testimonial dinner honoring Judge Joseph S. Longo, Hotel Statler, Hartford, Conn., 1957 June 20; 2 photographs (Box 2)
  - Oversize photographs, 1949-1955 (Box 4)
    - U.S. Naval Training Center, Sampson, N.Y., 1945 April 3 (Box 4)
      Longo is in the front row, second from the right.
    - Connecticut General Assembly, Committee on Judiciary, 1949; mounted on cardboard (Box 4)
      Names of members printed on mount.
    - Connecticut General Assembly, Committee on Judiciary, 1951; mounted on cardboard (Box 4)
    - State of Connecticut Senate, 1953; mounted on cardboard (Box 4)
      Signatures of members on mount.
    - Connecticut General Assembly, Judiciary Committee, 1955; mounted on cardboard (Box 4)
      Areas of cardboard are missing.
    - State of Connecticut Senate, undated; mounted on cardboard (Box 4)
- Series 3. Certificates, Awards, and Diplomas, 1932-1989
  - Alpha Phi Delta fraternity, 1932 November 18 (Box 4)
  - Yale University, B.A. diploma, 1936 June 16 (Box 4)
  - Gamma Eta Gamma legal fraternity, 1938 (Box 4)
  - Boston University, LL. B. diploma, 1939 June 12 (Box 4)
  - Certificate of admission to the Bar, State of Connecticut, 1939 July 11 (Box 4)
  - Appointment as Advisor to Registrants, Local Board No. 24, Connecticut by the Director of Selective Service, 1948 September 27 (Box 4)
  - Appointment as Judge of the City Court of Norwich, 1949 July 1 (Box 4)
  - Certificate of merit presented with the Selective Service Medal, undated (Box 4)
  - Certificate of honorary membership in the Young Italian-American Association of Hartford, Connecticut, 1951 November 18 (Box 4)
  - Certificate as an attorney of the United States District Court for the District of Connecticut, 1952 February 4 (Box 4)
  - Certificate of election as State Senator to represent the nineteenth senatorial district, 1952 November 26 (Box 4)
  - Certificate of election as State Senator to represent the nineteenth senatorial district, 1954 November 24; 1 item + photocopy (Box 4)
  - Certificate of admission to practice before the Board of Immigration Appeals and the Immigration and Naturalization Service, 1954 December 14 (Box 4)
  - Appointment as Judge of the Court of Common Pleas, 1957 May 31 (Box 4)
  - Certificate of appreciation in recognition of fifteen years service as a member of the Selective Service System, 1963 October 1 (Box 4)
  - Certificate of membership in the American Bar Association, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - Certificate of voting membership in the American Judicature Society, after 1967 (Box 4)
  - Appointment as Associate Judge of the Supreme Court and a Judge of the Superior Court, 1983 March 30 (Box 4)
  - Official citation in recognition of retirement as Senior Associate Justice of the Connecticut Supreme Court, 1984 October 18 (Box 4)
    Issued by the General Assembly. Introduced by Lieutenant Governor Joseph J. Fauliso.
  - Citation in recognition of 28 years of service as a member of the Connecticut Judiciary, 1985 May 20 (Box 4)
    Issued by the Connecticut Bar Association.
  - Boston University School of Law Alumni Award for distinguished public service, 1989 May 20 (Box 4)
  - Boston University 50th anniversary of graduation with Juris Doctor degree, 1989 May 21 (Box 4)